<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles of peace, commerce, &amp; alliance, between the crowns of Great Britain and Spain concluded in a treaty at Madrid the 13/23 day of May, in the year of our Lord God, 1667 / translated out of Latin.</title>
            <title>Treaties, etc. Spain, 1667 May 23</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2911</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8549</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12924396</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12924396</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95447</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32181)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95447)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 732:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles of peace, commerce, &amp; alliance, between the crowns of Great Britain and Spain concluded in a treaty at Madrid the 13/23 day of May, in the year of our Lord God, 1667 / translated out of Latin.</title>
                  <title>Treaties, etc. Spain, 1667 May 23</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>Philip IV, King of Spain, 1605-1665.</author>
                  <author>Spain. Treaties, etc. England and Wales, 1667 May 23.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the assigns of John Bill and Christopher Barker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] In the Savoy :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Added t.p. on p. [33]: The copy of a patent, containing several gracious priviledges lately granted by the High and Mighty Philip the Fourth, King of Spain, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:95447:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:95447:1"/>
                  <p>ARTICLES OF Peace, Commerce, &amp; Alliance, Between the CROWNS
OF Great Britain AND SPAIN. CONCLUDED In a Treaty at MADRID the 13/23. day of
<hi>May,</hi> in the Year of our LORD GOD, 1667.</p>
                  <p>Tranſlated out of Latin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Command.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the <hi>SAVOY,</hi> Printed by the Aſſigns of <hi>John
Bill</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Barker,</hi> Printers to the Kings moſt
Excellent Majeſty. 1667.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:95447:2"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95447:2"/>
                  <hi>Articles of Peace, Commerce, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance,
between the Crowns of</hi> Great Britain <hi>and</hi> Spain.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, It is Agreed and Concluded,</hi> That from this day
forward there ſhall be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Crowns of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and
<hi>Spain,</hi> a General, Good, Sincere, True, Firm and Perfect Amity,
Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and Peace, which ſhall endure for ever, and be obſerved
inviolably, as well by Land, as by Sea and Freſh-waters; and alſo between
the Lands, Countries, Kingdoms, Dominions and Territories, belonging un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or
under the obedience of either of them; And that their Subjects, People, and
Inhabitants reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of what condition, degree or quality ſoever,
from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95447:3"/>henceforth reciprocally, ſhall help,
aſſiſt, and ſhew to one another all manner of Love, good Offices, and
Friendſhip.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>That neither of the ſaid Kings, nor their reſpective People,
Subjects or Inhabitants within their Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, upon any pretence, may in
publick or ſecret, do, or procure to be done, any thing againſt the other,
in any Place, by Sea or by Land, nor in the Ports or Rivers of the one or the
other, but ſhall treat one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other with all Love and Friendſhip; and may
by Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and by Land, freely and ſecurely paſs into the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines,
Countries, Lands, Kingdoms, Iſlands, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, Cities, Towns, Villages,
wall'd or without wall, fortified or unfortified, their Havens and Ports (where
hitherto Trade and Commerce hath been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed) and there trade, buy and
ſell, as well of and to the Inhabitants of the reſpective Places, as
thoſe of their own Nation, or any other Nation that ſhall be or come
there.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>That the ſaid Kings of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and
<hi>Spain,</hi> ſhall take care that their reſpective People and Subjects
from henceforward do abſtain from all Force, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or Wrong; and if any
injury ſhall be done by either of the ſaid Kings, or by the People or
Subjects of either of them, to the People or Subjects of the other, againſt
the Articles of this Alliance, or againſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95447:3"/>common Right, there ſhall not therefore be
given Letters of Repriſal, Matque, or Counter-marque by any of the
Confederates, until ſuch time as juſtice is ſought and followed in the
ordinary courſe of Law: But if juſtice be denied or delayed, then the King
whoſe People or Inhabitants have received harm, ſhall ask it of the other,
by whom (as is ſaid) the juſtice ſhall have been denied or delayed, or of
the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that ſhall be by the one King or the other appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to receive and hear ſuch Demands, to the end that all ſuch differences may
be compounded in friendſhip, or according to Law. But if there ſhould yet
be a delay or juſtice ſhould not be done, nor ſatisfaction gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven within
ſix months after having the ſame ſo deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, then may be given Letters
of Repriſal, Marque or Counter-marque.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>That between the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the King of
<hi>Spain,</hi> and their reſpective People, Subjects and Inhabitants, as
well upon Sea as upon Land and Freſh-water, in all and every their Kingdoms,
Lands, Countries, Dominions, Confines, Territories, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, Iſlands,
Plantations, Cities, Villages, Towns, Ports, Rivers, Creeks, Bayes, Streights
and Currents, where hitherto Trade and Commerce hath been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed, there
ſhall be free Trade and Commerce, in ſuch way and manner, that without
ſafe Conduct, and without general or particular Licence, the People and
Subjects of each other may freely, as well by Land as by Sea and Freſh-water,
Navigate and go into their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95447:4"/>ſaid Countries, Kingdoms, Dominions, and all
the Cities, Ports, Currents, Bayes, Diſtricts, and other places thereof, and
may enter into any P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt with their Ships laden or empty, Carriage or Carriages
wherein to bring their Merchandiſe, and there buy and ſell what and how
much they pleaſe, and alſo at juſt and reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able rates provide
themſelves with proviſions and other neceſſary things for their
ſubſiſtence and voyage; and alſo may repair their Ships and carriages,
and from thence again freely depart with their Ships, Carriages, Goods,
Merchandiſe and Eſtate, and return to their own Countries, or to ſuch
other Place as they ſhall think fit, without any Moleſtation or Impediment,
ſo that they pay the Duties and Cuſtoms which ſhall be due, and ſaving
to either ſide the Laws and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their Country.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>Item, It is likewiſe agreed, That for the Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſes which
the Subjects of the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> ſhall buy in
<hi>Spain,</hi> or other the Kingdoms or Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the King of
<hi>Spain,</hi> and ſhall carry in their own Ships, or in Ships hired or lent
unto them, no new Cuſtoms, Toll, Tenths, Subſidies, or other Rights or
Duties whatſoever ſhall be taken or encreaſed, other then thoſe which
in the like caſe the Natives them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and all other ſtrangers are
obliged to pay; and the Subjects aforeſaid buying, ſelling and contracting
for their Merchandiſes, as well in reſpect of the Prices, as of all Duties
to be paid, ſhall enjoy the ſame pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges which are allowed to the
natural Subjects of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95447:4"/>
                     <hi>Spain;</hi> and may buy, and lade their Ships
with ſuch Goods and Merchan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>; which ſaid Ships be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laden, and
Cuſtoms paid for the Goods, ſhall not be detained in Port upon any pretence
whatſoever; nor ſhall the Laders, Merchants, or Factors who bought and
loaded the Goods aforeſaid be queſtioned after the departure of the ſaid
Ships, for any matter or thing whatſoever concerning the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>And to the end that the Officers and Miniſters of all Cities,
Towns and Villages belonging to either, may neither demand nor take from the
reſpective Merchants and People, greater Taxes, Duties, Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends,
Recompences, Gifts, or any other charges, then what ought to be taken by vertue
of this Treaty; and that the ſaid Merchants and People may know and
underſtand with certainty what is ordained in all things touching this; It is
agreed and concluded, That Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Liſts ſhall be put up at the Doors
of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom-houſes and Regiſtries of all the Cities, Villages and
Towns of, or appertaining to one or the other King where ſuch Rights and
Exciſes or Cuſtoms are uſually paid; in which, how much, and of what
quality ſuch Rights, Cuſtoms, Subſidies and Payments, either to the Kings
or any the aforeſaid Officers are allowed, ſhall be put down in writing,
declaring aſwell the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of what is imported, as what is carried out.
And if any Officer, or any other in his name upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever,
in publick or ſecret, directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly, ſhall ask or receive of any
Merchant or other
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95447:5"/>perſon reſpectively; any ſum of money or
other thing, by the name of Right, Due, Stipend, Allowance, or Recompence
(though it be by the way of voluntary Donative) more or otherwiſe then
aforeſaid, the ſaid Officer or his Deputy being in ſuch manner guilty and
convict before a competent Judge in the Country where the Crime is committed,
ſhall be put in Priſon for three months, and ſhall pay thrice the value
of the thing ſo received; of which the half ſhall be for the King of the
Country where the Crime is committed, and the other half for the Denunciator,
for the which he may ſue his Right before any competent Judge of the Country
where it ſhall happen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="part">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>That it ſhall be lawful for the Subjects of the King of
<hi>Great Britain,</hi> to bring out, and carry into <hi>Spain,</hi> and all or
any Lands and Dominions of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> (where heretofore they
have uſed Trade and Commerce) and trade there with all kind of
Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, Cloaths, Manufactures, and things of the Kingdom of <hi>Great
Britain,</hi> and the Manufactures, Goods, Fruits, and kinds of the Iſlands,
Towns and Plantations to him appertaining, and what ſhall have been bought by
Engliſh Factors on this ſide, or farther on the other ſide of the Cape of
<hi>Buena Eſperanca,</hi> without being inforced to declare to whom, or for
what price they ſell their ſaid Merchandiſe and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, or being
moleſted for the errors of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Ships, or others, in the
entry of the Goods; and at their pleaſure to return again out of the
Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95447:5"/>of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> with all, or any
Goods, Eſtates and Merchandiſe, to any of the Territories, Iſlands,
Dominions and Countries of the King of <hi>England,</hi> or to any other Place,
paying the Rights and Tributes mentioned in the antecedent Chapters; and the
reſt of all their lading which is not brought to Land, they may detain, keep
and carry away in their ſaid Ship or Ships, Veſſel or Veſſels again,
without paying any Right or Impoſition whatſoever for it, as if therewith
they had never been within any Bay or Port of the Catholique King. And all the
Goods, Eſtates, Merchandiſe, Ships or other Veſſels, with any things
introduced into the Dominions or Places of the Crown of <hi>Great Britain</hi>
as Prizes, and judged for ſuch in the ſaid Dominions and Places, ſhall be
taken for Goods and Merchandiſe of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo
by the intention of this Article.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="part">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>That the Subjects and Vaſſals of the Moſt Serene King of
<hi>Great Britain</hi> may bring and carry to all and ſingular the Dominions
of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> any Fruits and Commodities of the
<hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by teſtimony of the Deputies of the
<hi>Eaſt-Indy</hi> Company in <hi>London,</hi> that they are of, or have come
from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conqueſts, Plantations or Factories, with like
priviledge, and according to what is allowed to the Subjects of the United
Provinces, by the Royal <hi>Cedulas</hi> of <hi>Contravando</hi> bearing date
the 27. of <hi>June,</hi> and the 3. of <hi>July</hi> 1663. and publiſhed on
the 30. of <hi>June,</hi> and 4. of <hi>July</hi> the ſame year. And for what
may
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95447:6"/>concern both the <hi>Indies,</hi> and any other
Parts whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> doth grant to the King of
<hi>Great Britain</hi> and his Subjects, all that is granted to the United
States of the Low-Countreys and their Subjects, in their Treaty of
<hi>Munſter</hi> 1648. Point for Point, in as full and ample manner as if the
ſame were herein particularly inſerted, the ſame Rules being to be
obſerved whereunto the Subjects of the ſaid Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States are obliged, and
mutual Offices of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to be performed from one ſide to the
other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="part">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>That the Subjects of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
buying and ſelling in any of the Kingdoms, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, Iſlands, Ports or
Territories of the ſaid King of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhall have, uſe, and
enjoy all the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and Immunities, which the ſaid King hath granted
and confirmed to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants that reſide in
<hi>Andaluzia,</hi> by his Royal <hi>Cedulas</hi> or Orders, dated the 19. day
of <hi>March,</hi> the 26. day of <hi>June,</hi> and the 9. day of
<hi>November</hi> 1645. His Catholique Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty by theſe preſents
reconfirming the ſame as a part of this Treaty between the two Crowns. And to
the end that it be manifeſt to all, It is conſented, That the ſaid
Schedules (as to the whole ſubſtance thereof) be paſſed and transferred
to the body of the preſent Articles, in the name and favour of all and
ſingular the Subjects of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> reſiding and
trading in any Places whatſoever within his Catholique Majeſties
Dominions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="part">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95447:6"/>
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>That the Ships, or any other Veſſels that ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to
the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> or his Subjects, Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating into the King
of <hi>Spain's</hi> Dominions, or any of his Ports, ſhall not be viſited by
the Judges of Counterband, or by any other Officer or Perſon, by his own, or
by any other Authority; nor ſhall any Souldiers, armed men or other Officers
or Perſons, be put on board any of the ſaid Ships or Veſſels; nor
ſhall the Officers of the Cuſtom-houſe of the one or the other Party,
ſearch in any Veſſels or Ships belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the People of the one or the
other, which ſhall enter into their Regions, Dominions, or reſpective
Ports, until their ſaid Ships or Veſſels are unladen, or until they have
carried on ſhore all the Lading and Merchandiſe which they declare they
reſolve to diſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barque in the ſaid Port; nor ſhall the Captain,
Maſter, or any other of the Company of the ſaid Ships be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, or
they or their Boats detained on ſhore; but in the interim, Officers of the
Cuſtom-houſe may be put on board the ſaid Veſſels or Ships, ſo they
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed not the number of three for each Ship, to ſee that no Goods or
Merchandiſe be landed out of the ſaid Ships or Veſſels, without paying
ſuch Duties as by theſe Articles either Party is obliged to pay, which
ſaid Officers are to be without any charge to the Ship or Ships, Veſſel
or Veſſels, their Commanders, Mariners, Company, Merchants, Factors, or
Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. And when it happens that the Maſter or Owner
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95447:7"/>of any Ship ſhall declare that the whole
Lading of his ſaid Ship is to be diſcharged in any Port, the Entry of the
ſaid Lading ſhall be made in the Cuſtom-houſe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the uſual
manner; and if after the Entry made, any other Goods be found in the ſaid
Ship or Ships, more then what are contained in the ſaid Entry, eight work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
dayes ſhall be allowed them on which they may work (which ſhall be reckoned
from the day they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to unlade) to the end, that the concealed Goods may be
entred, and the Confiſcation of them prevented: And in caſe that in the
time limited, the Entry or Manifeſtation of them ſhall not have been made,
then ſuch particular Goods only, which ſhall be found as aforeſaid,
though the unlading be not finiſhed, ſhall be confiſcated, and not any
other; nor ſhall other trouble be given, or puniſhment inflicted on the
Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant or Owner of the Ship; and when the Ships or Veſſels are reladen,
they may have freedom to go out again.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="part">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>That the Ship or Ships appertaining to the one or the other King,
or to their reſpective People and Subjects, that ſhall enter into any
Ports, Lands or Dominions of the one or the other, and ſhall diſcharge any
part of their Goods and Merchandiſes in any Port or Haven, being conſigned
with the reſt to other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, within or without the ſaid Dominions,
ſhall not be obliged to regiſter or pay the Rights of any other Goods or
Merchandiſe, then of that which they ſhall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95447:7"/>unlade in the ſaid Port or Haven, nor be
conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ned to give Bond for the Goods they ſhall carry to other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
nor any other ſecurity, if it be not in caſe of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, Debt, Treaſon,
or other capital Crime.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="part">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>Whereas the one moity of the Cuſtom of all For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Goods and
Merchandiſe imported into <hi>England,</hi> is allowed and returned back to
the Importer, if the ſaid Goods be exported out of the ſaid Kingdom with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
twelve moneths after their firſt Landing, upon Oath made that they are the
ſame Goods which paid Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom inwards, and that if they be not re-ſhipt
within the ſaid twelve months, yet they may at all times be exported without
paying any Cuſtom or Duty out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: It is therefore agreed, That if any the
Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> ſhall hereafter Land any
Goods or Merchandiſe, of what growth or nature ſoever they be, in any of
the Ports of his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Majeſty, and having entred them, and paid the
Cuſtom which by this Treaty ought to be paid, and ſhall afterwards deſire
to tranſport them, or any part of them, to any other Place whatſoever, for
a better Market, it ſhall and may be lawful for him or them ſo to do
freely, without paying or being demanded any other Cuſtom or Duty at all for
the ſame, he or they making Oath, if required thereunto, that they are the
ſame Goods for which Cuſtom was paid at their Landing; And in caſe that
the Subjects, People and Inhabitants of the Dominions of either part ſhall
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade, or have in any City, Town or Village reſpectively,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95447:8"/>any Goods, Merchandiſes, Fruits or Eſtates,
and have paid the Cuſtoms due, according to what hath been declared, and
after that, not being able to put them off, ſhall reſolve to remit them to
ſome other City, Town or Village of the ſaid Dominions, they may not only
do it without difficulty or impediment, and without paying other Rights then
what were due at their Entry, but likewiſe the Cuſtom or Rights ſhall not
be paid again in any other part of the ſaid Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, bringing Certificates
from the Officers of the Cuſtom-houſe, that they were paid before in the
due form. And the chief Farmers and Commiſſioners of the King of
<hi>Spain's</hi> Rents in all Places, or ſome other Officer or Officers to be
appointed for that purpoſe, ſhall at all times permit and ſuffer the
Tranſportation of all ſuch Goods and Merchandiſes from place to place,
and give ſufficient certificate to the Owners thereof, or their Aſſignes,
of their having paid their Cuſtom at their firſt Landing, whereby they may
be carried to, and Landed at any other Port or Place of the ſaid
Juriſdiction, free from all Duties or Impediments whatſoever, as
aforeſaid, ſaving always the Right of any third Perſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="part">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>That it ſhall be lawful for the Ships belonging to the Subjects
of the one or other King, to anchor in the Roads or Bays of either, without
being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to enter into Port; and in caſe they be
neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to enter thereinto, either by diſtreſs of weather, fear
of enemies, Pirates, or any other accident, in caſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95447:8"/>the ſaid Ships be not bound to an Enemies
Port, and carrying thither Contraband Goods (whereof with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome clear
proof, they ſhall not be queſtioned) it ſhall be lawful for the ſaid
Subjects, to return to Sea freely when they pleaſe, with their Ships and
Goods, ſo as they do not break bulk, or expoſe any thing to ſale; and
that when they caſt anchor, or enter the Ports aforeſaid, they be not
moleſted or viſited; and it ſhall ſuffice that in this caſe they
ſhew their Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports or Sea-papers, which being ſeen by the
reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Officers of either King, the ſaid Ships ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn freely
to Sea without any moleſtation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="part">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>And if any Ship or Ships belonging to the Subjects and Merchants
of the one or the other, entring into Bayes, or in the open Sea, ſhall be
encountred by the Ships of the ſaid Kings, or of Privateers their Subjects;
the ſaid Ships, to prevent all diſorders, ſhall not come within
Canon-ſhot, but ſhall ſend their Long-Boat or Pinnace to the
Merchant-Ship, and only two or three men on board, to whom the Maſter or
Owner ſhall ſhew his Paſsports and Sea-Letters, according to the form
which ſhall be inſerted at the end of this Treaty, whereby not only the
Ships Lading, but the place to which ſhe belongs, and as well the Maſter
and Owners name, as the name of the Ship may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; by which means the
quality of the Ship, and her Maſter or Owner will be ſufficiently known, as
alſo the Commodities ſhe carries, whether they be Contraband, or not; to
the which Paſsports and Sea-Letters, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95447:9"/>faith and credit ſhall be given, ſo much the
rather, for that as well on the part of the King of <hi>England,</hi> as of the
King of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſome Counter ſignes ſhall be given (if it ſhall
be found neceſſary) whereby their authenticalneſs may the better appear,
and that they may not be in any wiſe falſified.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="part">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>If any prohibited Merchandiſe or Goods ſhall be exported from
the Kingdoms, Dominions and Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of either of the ſaid Kings, by the
reſpective People or Subjects of the one or the other, in ſuch caſe the
prohibited Goods ſhall be only confiſcated, and not the other Goods;
neither ſhall the Delinquent incur any other puniſhment, except the ſaid
Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſhall carry out from the reſpective Kingdoms or Dominions of
the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> the proper Coin, Wooll, or Fullers-earth of
the ſaid Kingdoms, or ſhall carry out of the reſpective Kingdoms or
Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of the ſaid King of <hi>Spain,</hi> any Gold or Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, wrought
or unwrought; in either of which caſes, the Laws of the reſpective
Countreys are to take place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="part">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>That it ſhall be lawful for the People and Subjects of both
Kings, to have acceſs to the reſpective Ports of the one and the other, and
there remain, and depart again with the ſame freedom, not only with their
Ships, and other Veſſels for Trade and Commerce,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95447:9"/>but alſo with their other Ships fitted for
War, armed, and diſpoſed to reſiſt and engage the Enemy, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving
by ſtreſs of weather to repair their Ships, or furniſh themſelves with
Proviſions; ſo that entring willingly, they be not ſo numerous, that they
give juſt occaſion of ſuſpition, to which end they are not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
the number of Eight, nor continue in their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, nor about their Ports,
longer time then they ſhall have juſt cauſe, for the repair of their
Ships, to take in Proviſions or other neceſſary things, much leſs be
the occaſion of interrupting the free Commerce, and coming in of other Ships,
of Nations in Amity with either King; and when an unuſual number of Men of
War, by accident ſhall come unto any Port, it ſhall not be lawful for them
to come into the ſaid Ports or Havens, not having firſt obtained
permiſſion of the King unto whom the ſaid Ports do belong, or the
Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the ſaid Ports, if they be not forced there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into by ſtreſs
of weather or other neceſſity, to avoid the danger of the Sea, and in
ſuch caſe they ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently acquaint the Governour or chief
Magiſtrate of the Place with the cauſe of their coming; nor ſhall they
remain there any longer time then the ſaid Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour or Magiſtrate ſhall
think convenient, or do any act of Hoſtility in ſuch Ports, that may prove
of prejudice to the one or the other of the ſaid Kings.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="part">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:95447:10"/>
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>That neither the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> nor the
King of <hi>Spain,</hi> by any Mandate general, nor particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, nor for any
cauſe whatſoever, ſhall Embarque or detain, hinder or take for his
reſpective ſervice, any Merchant, Maſter of a Ship, Pilot or Mariner
their Ships, Merchandiſe, Cloaths or other Goods belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto the one or
the other, in their Ports or Waters, if it be not that either of the ſaid
Kings, or the Perſons to whom the Ships belong, be firſt advertiſed
thereof, and do agree thereunto; Provided that this ſhall not be conſtrued
to hinder or interrupt the ordinary courſe of Juſtice and Law in either
Country.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="part">
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>That the Merchants and Subjects of the one and the other King,
their Factors and Servants, as alſo their Ships, Maſters and Mariners, may
as well going as coming, upon Sea and other Waters, as in the Havens and Ports
of the one and the other reſpectively, carry and uſe all kind of Arms,
Defenſive and Offenſive, without being obliged to regiſter them, as
alſo upon Land to carry and uſe them for their defence, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the
cuſtom of the Place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="part">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>That the Captains, Officers and Mariners of the Ships belonging to
the People and Subjects of either
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95447:10"/>Party, may not commence an Action, nor hinder
or bring trouble upon their own Ships, their Captains, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers or Mariners in
the reſpective Kingdoms, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, Lands, Countries or Places of the other,
for their Wages or Salaries, or under any other pretence. Nor may they put
themſelves, or be received, by what pretext or colour ſoever, into the
Service or Protection of the King of <hi>England,</hi> or King of
<hi>Spain,</hi> or their Arms; but if any controverſie happen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
Merchants and Maſters of Ships, or between Maſters and Mariners, the
compoſing thereof ſhall be left to the Conſul of the Nation, but after
ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as he who ſhall not ſubmit to the Arbitrement, may appeal
to the ordinary Juſtice of the Place where he is ſubject.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="part">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>And to the end that all Impediments be taken away, and that the
Merchants and Adventurers of the Kingdoms of <hi>Great Britain</hi> be
permitted to return to <hi>Brabant, Flanders,</hi> and other the Provinces of
the Low-Countries, under the Juriſdiction of the King of <hi>Spain;</hi>
Foraſmuch as it hath been thought convenient, that all, and any the Laws,
Edicts, and Acts by which the Importation of Cloth, or any other Woollen
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture, of what kind ſoever, dyed, or undyed, raill'd, or unmill'd,
into <hi>Flanders,</hi> or the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, hath been prohibited, be
revoked and diſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null'd; and that if any Right, Tribute, Impoſition,
Charge or Money, hath been, with permiſſion, or otherwiſe, put upon
Cloaths, or any of the aforeſaid Woollen Manufactures ſo imported (except
the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95447:11"/>Tribute upon every piece of Cloth, and
propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably upon every other Woollen Manufacture, agreeable to the ancient
Treaties and Agreements between the then Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and the
Dukes of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and Governours of the Low-Countries) the ſame
ſhould be altogether void, and no ſuch Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute or Impoſition from
henceforth impoſed, or put upon the ſaid Clothes or Manufactures, for no
cauſe or pretext whatſoever; And that all the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, trading in any of the ſaid Provinces, their Factors, Servants, or
Commiſſioners, ſhould enjoy from henceforward, all the Priviledges,
Exemptions, Immunities and Benefits, which formerly have been agreed and given
by the aforeſaid ancient Treaties and Agreements, between the then Kings of
<hi>England,</hi> and the Dukes of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and Governours of the
Low-Countries: It is therefore agreed, That Deputies ſhall be named by the
King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> who meeting with the Marqueſs of
<hi>Caſtelrodrigo,</hi> or the Governour of thoſe Provinces for the time
being, or any other Miniſters of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſufficiently
authoriſed in this behalf, ſhall friendly Treat and Conclude here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; and
alſo ſuch further Priviledges, Immunities, and neceſſary Exemptions,
ſuitable to the preſent ſtate of Affairs, ſhall be granted for the
encouragement of the ſaid Merchants and Adventurers, and for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity
of their Trade and Commerce, as ſhall be agreed upon in a ſpecial Treaty,
that ſhall be made between both the Kings, touching this Particular.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="part">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95447:11"/>
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>The Subjects and Inhabitants of the Kingdoms and Dominions of the
Moſt Serene Kings of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi>
reſpectively, ſhall with all ſecurity and liberty, Sail to, and Traffick,
in all the Kingdoms, Eſtates, or Countries, which are or ſhall be in Peace,
Amity, or Neutrality with the one or the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="part">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>And they ſhall not be diſturbed or diſquieted in that
liberty, by the Ships or Subjects of the ſaid Kings reſpectively, by
reaſon of the hoſtilities which are or may be hereafter between either of
the ſaid Kings, and the aforeſaid Kingdoms, Countries, and States, or any
of them, which ſhall be in Friendſhip or Neutrality with the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="part">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>And in caſe that within the ſaid Ships reſpectively, be
found by the aboveſaid means, any Merchandiſe here under mentioned, being
of Contraband, and Prohibited, they ſhall be taken out and confiſcated,
before the Admiralty, or other competent Judges; but for this reaſon, the
Ship, and the other free and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Commodities which ſhall be found
therein, ſhall in no wiſe be either ſeized or confiſcated.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="part">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95447:12"/>
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>Moreover, for better prevention of the differences which might
ariſe touching the meaning of forbidden Merchandiſe, and of Contraband; It
is declared and agreed, That under this name ſhall be comprehended all
Fire-Arms, as Ordnance, Muskets, Mortar-pieces, Petards, Bumbs, Granadoes,
Fire-crancels, Fire-balls, Musket-reſts, Bandeliers, Gunpowder, Match,
Salt-peter, and Bullets; likewiſe under the name of forbidden Merchandiſe,
are underſtood all other Arms, as Pikes, Swords, Pots, Helmets, Backs, and
Breaſts, Halberds, Javelins, and ſuch like Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; Under this name is
likewiſe forbidden the tranſportation of Souldiers, Horſes, their
Harnaſſes, Caſes of Piſtols, Holſters, Belts, and other Furniture,
formed and compoſed for the uſe of War.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="part">
                  <head>XXV.</head>
                  <p>Likewiſe, to prevent all manner of diſpute and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, It
is agreed, That under that name of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Merchandiſe, and of Contraband,
ſhall not be comprehended Wheat, Rye, Barley, or other Grains, or Pulſe,
Salt, Wine, Oyle, and generally whatſoever belongs to the ſuſtaining and
nouriſhing of life, but they ſhall remain free, as likewiſe all other
Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſes not comprehended in the preceding Article; and the
tranſportation of them ſhall be free and permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, although it be to the
Towns and Places of Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95447:12"/>unleſs ſuch Towns and Places be beſieged,
block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, or ſurrounded.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="part">
                  <head>XXVI.</head>
                  <p>It is alſo agreed, That whatſoever ſhall be found laden by
the Subjects or Inhabitants of the Kingdoms and Dominions of either of the
ſaid Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> aboard the Ships of the
Enemies of the other, though it be not forbidden Merchandiſe, ſhall be
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated, with all things elſe which ſhall be found within the ſaid
Ships without exception or reſerve.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="part">
                  <head>XXVII.</head>
                  <p>That the Conſul which hereafter ſhall reſide in any of the
Dominions of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> for the help and protection of the
Subjects of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> ſhall be named by the King of
<hi>Great Britain,</hi> and he ſo named, ſhall have and exerciſe the
ſame power and authority in the execution of his charge, as any other
Conſul hath formerly had in the Dominions of the ſaid King of
<hi>Spain;</hi> and in like manner the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Conſul reſiding
in <hi>England,</hi> ſhall enjoy as much authority as the Conſuls of any
other Nation have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto enjoyed in that Kingdom.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="part">
                  <head>XXVIII.</head>
                  <p>And that the Laws of Commerce that are obtained by Peace, may not
remain unfruitful, as would fall out if the Subjects of the King of <hi>Great
Britain,</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:95447:13"/>when they go to, come from, or remain in the
Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions or Lordſhips of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> by reaſon of their
Commerce or other buſineſs, ſhould be moleſted for caſe of
Conſcience; therefore that the Commerce be ſecure, and without danger, as
well upon Land as at Sea, the ſaid King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhall provide,
that the Subjects of the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> ſhall not be
agrieved contrary to the Laws of Commerce, and that none of them ſhall be
moleſted or diſturbed for their Conſcience, ſo long as they give no
publique ſcandal or offence; and the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain</hi>
ſhall, likewiſe provide, for the ſame reaſons, that the Subjects of the
King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhall not be moleſted or diſturbed for their
Conſcience againſt the Laws of Commerce, ſo long as they give no publique
ſcandal or offence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="part">
                  <head>XXIX.</head>
                  <p>That the People and Subjects reſpectively of one Kingdom, in the
Dominions, Territories, Regions or Colonies of the other, ſhall not be
compelled to ſell their Merchandiſe for Braſs-metal-Coin, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change
them for other Coin or things, againſt their will; or having ſold them, to
receive the payment in other ſpecies, then what they bargained for,
not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any Law or other Cuſtom contrary to this Article.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="part">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:95447:13"/>
                  <head>XXX.</head>
                  <p>That the Merchants of both Nations, and their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Servants
and Families, Commiſſioners, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by them employed; as alſo
Maſters of Ships, Pilots and Mariners, may remain freely and ſecurely in
the ſaid Dominions, Kingdoms and Territories of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſaid Kings,
and alſo in their Ports and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; and the People and Subjects of the one
King, may have, and with all freedom and ſecurity enjoy, in all the Lands and
Dominions whatſoever of the other, their proper Houſes to live in, their
Ware-houſes and Magazins for their Goods and Merchandiſe, which they
ſhall poſſeſs during the time for which they ſhall have taken, hired,
and agreed for them, without any Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="part">
                  <head>XXXI.</head>
                  <p>The Inhabitants and Subjects of the ſaid Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Kings, in
all the Lands and Places under the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the one or the other, ſhall
uſe and employ thoſe Advocates, Proctors, Scriveners, Agents and
Solicitors, whom they think fit, the which ſhall be left to their choice, and
conſented to by the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Judges, as often as there ſhall be
occaſion; and they ſhall not be conſtrained to ſhew their Books and
Papers of Accompt to any perſon, if it be not to give evidence for the
avoiding Law-ſuits and Controverſies; neither ſhall they be embarqued,
detained, or taken out of their hands, upon any pretence whatſoever. And
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95447:14"/>it ſhall be permitted to the People and
Subjects of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther King, in the reſpective. Places where they ſhall
reſide, to keep their Books of Accompt, Traffick and Correſpondence in what
Language they pleaſe, in <hi>Engliſh, Spaniſh, Dutch,</hi> or any other,
the which ſhall not be moleſted, or ſubject to any Inquiſition. And
whatſoever elſe hath been granted by either Party, concerning this
particular, to any other Nation, ſhall be underſtood likewiſe to be
granted here.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="part">
                  <head>XXXII.</head>
                  <p>That in caſe the Eſtate of any perſon or perſons ſhall
be ſequeſtred or ſeiſed on by any Court of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or Tribunal
whatſoever, within the Kingdoms and Dominions of either Party, and any
Eſtate or Debt happen to lie in the hands of the Delinquents belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>Bonâ ſide</hi> to the People and Subjects of the other, the ſaid
Eſtate or Debts ſhall not be confiſcated by any of the ſaid Tribunals,
but ſhall be reſtored to the true Owners <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> if they yet
remain, and if not, the value of them (according to the Contract and Agreement
which was made between the Parties) ſhall be reſtored within three moneths
after the ſaid ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="part">
                  <head>XXXIII.</head>
                  <p>That the Goods and Eſtates of the People and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the
one King, that ſhall die in the Countries, Lands and Dominions of the other,
ſhall be preſerved
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95447:14"/>for the lawful Heirs and Succeſſors of the
deceaſed; the right of any third Perſon alwayes reſerved.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="part">
                  <head>XXXIV.</head>
                  <p>That the Goods and Eſtates of the Subjects of the King of
<hi>Great Britain,</hi> that ſhall die without making a Will in the Dominions
of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhall be put into Inventory with their Papers,
Writings, and Books of Accompt, by the Conſul or other publique Miniſter of
the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and depoſited in the hands of two or
three Merchants that ſhall be named by the ſaid Conſul, or publique
Miniſter, to be kept for the Proprietors and Creditors; and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the
<hi>Cruzada,</hi> nor any other Judicatory whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſhall intermeddle
therein; which alſo in the like caſe ſhall be obſerved in
<hi>England</hi> towards the Subjects of the King of <hi>Spain.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="part">
                  <head>XXXV.</head>
                  <p>That a decent and convenient Burial-place ſhall be granted and
appointed to bury the bodies of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the King of <hi>Great
Britain,</hi> who ſhall die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Dominions of the King of
<hi>Spain.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="part">
                  <head>XXXVI.</head>
                  <p>If it ſhall happen hereafter that any difference fall out (which
God forbid) between the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the King of
<hi>Spain,</hi> whereby the mutual Commerce and good Correſpondence may be
endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95447:15"/>the reſpective Subjects and People of each
Party ſhall have notice thereof given them in time, that is to ſay, the
ſpace of ſix months, to tranſport their Merchandiſe and effects,
without giving them in that time any Moleſtation or trouble, or retaining or
embarquing their Goods or Perſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="part">
                  <head>XXXVII.</head>
                  <p>All Goods and Rights concealed or embarqued, Moveables,
Immoveables, Rents, Deeds, Debts, Credits, and the like, which have not with a
formal notice of the cauſe, and by a legal condemnation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the
Ordinary Juſtice been brought into the Royal Exchequer at the time of
concluding this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhall remain at the full and free diſpoſal of
the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors, their Heirs, or of thoſe who ſhall have their Right, with
all the Fruits, Rents and Emoluments thereof, and neither thoſe who have
concealed the ſaid Goods, nor their Heirs ſhall be moleſted forthis
cauſe by the Exchequers reſpectively; but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors, their Heirs, or
thoſe who ſhall have their Right, ſhall have for the ſaid Goods and
Rights their Action at Law, as for their own proper Goods and Eſtate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="part">
                  <head>XXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>It is agreed and Concluded, That the People and Subjects of the
King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhall have
and enjoy in the reſpective Lands, Seas, Ports, Havens, Roads and Territories
of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95447:15"/>the one or the other, and in all Places
whatſoever, the ſame Priviledges, Securities, Liberties and Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
whether they concern their Perſons or Trade, with all the beneficial
clauſes and circumſtances which have been granted, or ſhall be hereafter
granted by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſaid Kings, to the Moſt Chriſtian King, the
States General of the United Provinces, the Hans-Towns, or any other Kingdom or
State what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, in as full, ample, and beneficial manner, as if the ſame
were particularly mentioned and inſerted in this Treaty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="part">
                  <head>XXXIX.</head>
                  <p>In caſe any difference or diſpute ſhall happen on either
ſide concerning theſe Articles of Trade and Commerce, by either the
Officers of the Admiralty or other perſon whatſoever, in the one or the
other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; The complaint being preſented by the party concerned, to
their Majeſties, or to any of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, their ſaid Majeſties
ſhall cauſe the damages forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to be repaired, and all things, as they
are above agreed, to be duly executed; and in caſe, that in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of
time any frauds or inconveniencies be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in the Navigation and
Commerce between both Kingdoms, againſt which ſufficient prevention hath
not been made in theſe Articles, other proviſions may be hereafter mutually
agreed on, as ſhall be judged convenient, the preſent Treaty remaining
ſtill in full force and vigour,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="part">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:95447:16"/>
                  <head>XL.</head>
                  <p>It is likewiſe accorded and concluded, That the Moſt Serene
and Renowned Kings of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> ſhall
ſincerely, and faithfully obſerve and keep, and procure to be obſerved
and kept, by their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Inhabitants reſpectively, all and ſingular
the Capitulations in this preſent Treaty agreed and concluded: Neither
ſhall they directly or indirectly infringe the ſame, or conſent that the
ſame ſhall be infringed by any of their Subjects or Inhabitants. And they
ſhall ratifie and confirm all and ſingular the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions before accorded
by Letters Patents recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, in ſufficient, full and effectual form, and
the ſame ſo formed and made, ſhall interchangeably deliver, or cauſe to
be delivered faithfully and really, within four months after the date of
theſe preſents; and they ſhall then, aſſoon as conveniently may be,
cauſe this preſent Treaty of Peace and Amity to be publiſhed in all
Places, and in the manner accuſtomed.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated at <hi>Madrid,</hi> 
                        <date>the
13./23. day of <hi>May,</hi> in the Year of our Lord,
1667.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:95447:16"/>
                  <head>The Form of Letters which ought to be given by the Towns and
Sea-Ports, to the Ships and Veſſels ſetting ſail from thence.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O all unto whom theſe Preſents ſhall come; We the
Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Conſuls, or chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate or Commiſſioners of the
Cuſtoms, of the City, Town or Province of <hi>N.</hi> do teſtifie and make
known, That <hi>N. N.</hi> Maſter of the Ship <hi>N.</hi> hath before Us,
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſolemn Oath declared, That the Ship <hi>N.</hi> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap>
Tun (more or leſs) of which he is at preſent Maſter, doth belong to the
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>N.</hi> in the Dominions of the Moſt Serene King of
<hi>Great Britain.</hi> And We, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring that the ſaid Maſter may be
aſſiſted in his Voyage and Buſineſs, do intreat all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in
general and particular, who ſhall meet him, and thoſe of all Places where
the ſaid Maſter ſhall come with the ſaid Ship and her
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95447:17"/>Merchandiſe, that they would admit him
favourably, treat him kindly, and receive the ſaid Ship into their Ports,
Bayes, Havens, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Dominions, permitting her quietly to ſail, paſs,
frequent, and Negotiate there, or in any other places, as ſhall ſeem good
to the ſaid Maſter, paying ſtill the Toll and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes which of right
ſhall be due. Which we will acknowledge gratefully upon the like occaſions.
In witneſs whereof, we have ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe Preſents, and ſealed them
with the Seal of our Town.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>WILL. GODOLPHIN.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Don</hi> PEDRO FERNANDEZ <hi>del Campo y
Angulo.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:95447:17"/>
                  <p>The Copy OF A PATENT, Containing Several Gracious Priviledges
lately Granted by the High and Mighty Philip the Fourth, <hi>KING of
SPAIN,</hi> &amp;c. Which are Confirmed by the foregoing Treaty, and whereof
mention is made in the Ninth Article of the ſaid Treaty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Command.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the <hi>SAVOY,</hi> Printed by the Aſſigns of <hi>John
Bill</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Barker,</hi> Printers to the Kings moſt
Excellent Majeſty. 1667.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:95447:18"/>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:95447:18"/>
                  <head>The Copy of a Patent containing ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Gracious
Priviledges lately granted by the High and Mighty <hi>PHILIP</hi> the Fourth,
King of <hi>Spain,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>ON PHILIP,</hi> By the Grace of God, King of
<hi>Caſtile, Leon, Arragon,</hi> the two <hi>Sicilies, Jeruſalem, Portugal,
Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre, Granado, Toledo, Valencia, Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, Majorca, Sivilla, Sardinia,
Cordoua, Corſega, Murica, Jaen,</hi> the <hi>Algarves, Algeſira,
Gibral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> the Iſlands of the <hi>Canaries,</hi> the <hi>Eaſt</hi>
and <hi>Weſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> Iſlands, and firm Land of the Ocean Sea,
Arch-Duke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundy, Brabant,</hi> and
<hi>Milan,</hi> Earl of <hi>Haſpurg, Flanders, Tiroll,</hi> and
<hi>Barcelona,</hi> Lord of <hi>Biſcay</hi> and <hi>Molina,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:95447:19"/>
                  <p>WHereas on the behalf of you <hi>Richard An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony,</hi> Conſul
of the Engliſh Nation, for your ſelf, and in the Name of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of
the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> it hath been ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto me, That by
vertue of the Peace which is concluded in this and that Realm, you do reſide
and trade in <hi>Andaluzia,</hi> and ſpecially in the Cities of
<hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> St. <hi>Lucar, Cadiz,</hi> and <hi>Malaga,</hi> deſiring me
to be pleaſed to confirm unto you the priviledges, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptions and faculties
which do belong unto you as well by the Articles of the ſaid Peace, as by the
Confirmations thereof, and other Favours and Graces which my Lord and Father of
glorious memory did grant unto you, and all ſuch others which have been given
you by the Crowns of my Realms of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Rortugal,</hi> and
to command that they may be in, and for all things obſerved and
accompliſhed unto you without any limitation, and for further aſſurance
to grant them anew unto you, with the qualities, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitudes and declarations
which ſhall be moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for you; and to ſet Penalties upon ſuch
as ſhall contradict, and not obſerve them unto you; and to the end it may
be known what they are, to grant them Copies thereof, or of that which my
favour ſhall be; And I taking the Premiſes into conſideration; and
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe for the occaſions which I have for my Wars, you have offered to
ſerve me with 2500. Duckets of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to be paid one Thouſand ready
money, and the remaining one Thouſand five Hundred in the Moneth of
<hi>April</hi> of this Year; whereof the Licentiate <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Moreno,</hi>
which in reverſion of <hi>Don Anthony de
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95447:19"/>Campo Redondoy Rio,</hi> Knight of the Order
of <hi>Santi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ago,</hi> one of my Council and Chamber, and of the Treaſury in
your name, and by vertue of your power did acknowledge a Writing of Obligation
in form before <hi>John Cortez de la Cruz,</hi> my Notary, I do hold it for
good; And by theſe Preſents of my own moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and certain knowledge, and
Royal and abſolute Power, which I in this behalf will make uſe of, and do
uſe as an abſolute King and Lord, not acknowledging any Superior in matters
Temporal, do confirm and approve the Priviledges, Exemptions, and Faculties
which do belong unto you as well by the Articles of the ſaid Peace, as by the
Confirmation thereof; and alſo the other favours and graces which my Lord and
Father did grant unto you, and others whatſoever, which have been given by my
Crowns of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Portugal</hi> unto the ſaid Subjects, in
and for all things as therein, and every thing and part thereof is ſpecified,
contained, and declared, to the end they may be firm, ſtable, and of value,
and be obſerved, kept and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed unto you: For my deliberate intent
and will is, that all thoſe of the ſaid Nation ſhall enjoy thereof
without any limitation, in ſuch manner, that, during the time the ſaid
Engliſhmen ſhall reſide in <hi>Andaluzia,</hi> neither you nor they may
be charged with any Office or publick Charge, nor Council, Tutor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
Curatorſhip, Receivers or Treaſurers, although they be of Cuſtomers and
Millions, or other Services which concern my Royal Treaſury; and much leſs
they may demand of you any Loans or donations, or take from you any Rights, or
your Rents, Horſes, or Slaves: And to do you the more favour or grace
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95447:20"/>to that which is agreed by the ſaid Peace,
I do will and promiſe that you ſhall and may deal and trade freely, and
ſell your Merchandiſe and Fruits, and buy thoſe of my Realms, and carry
them forth, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving that which is ordained and commanded by the Laws and
Statutes which make mention thereof, and paying to my Royal Treaſury the
Duties or Cuſtoms which ought to be paid, prohibiting, as I do prohibit and
command, not to take from you by force any Merchandiſes, Wheat, or Barley,
although it be for the making ready or furniſhing my Armies, Fleets, or
Gallions, nor for Purveyors or Stewards; and the Priviledges are to be
concerning the Wheat and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley according to the Tun; and concerning the other
things and Merchandiſes, as you ſhall conclude and agree: but they may not
take them out of your Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion until they have paid for them,
unleſs for the ſame there be leave given, that they do not moleſt and
trouble you. And foraſmuch as many of you do treat to bring into the Ports of
<hi>Andaluſia,</hi> the City of <hi>Sivil,</hi> and other places, great
quantity of <hi>New-found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land-Fiſh,</hi> and other ſorts of dry and
ſalted Fiſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are Victuals which are very neceſſary; and
that you have been and are put to great Charges, and are much troubled, I do
will and command to be kept the Ordinance of the City of <hi>Sivil,</hi>
whereby it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, that thoſe which come in with dry or ſalted
Fiſh, there ſhall not be any Price or Rate ſet upon them, but they
ſhall be permitted to ſell at ſuch a Price as they ſhall think good;
and it ſhall not be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to manifeſt them any more then unto my
Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers which receive my Royal Rents: and if the Ships
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95447:20"/>wherein the ſaid Fiſh is brought be great
Ships, that they cannot go up the River, and that the ſame be put into
Barques or Lighters, the Judge of the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty nor any other perſon may not
put any Waiters or Keepers into the Barques or Lighters at the charge of the
Owners of them.</p>
                  <p>And I do alſo command, That if the ſaid Fiſh ſhall
appear to be rotten, and that it cannot be ſpent, that it be burnt, or thrown
into the Sea; and that for this cauſe there ſhall not be any Cauſe or
Action commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt the Owners thereof, or perſons which ſhall
ſell it, nor they ſhall not be impriſoned, nor informed againſt: And
foraſmuch as the Adminiſters of the Cuſtoms, and others of divers duties
which are recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the Fruits and Merchandiſes, do uſe when any body
doth inform, to have the perſon Impriſoned which ſheweth himſelf to be
party, whereby happeneth to men of Trade great diſcredit, charges, and
vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; My Will is, and I do command, that in the ſaid Information there
ſhall be only proceeded againſt the Merchandiſes, and not againſt the
perſons; but they ſhall be permitted (as I do permit them) to make, and
they ſhall make their defences in the ſaid Vexation. And foraſmuch
alſo, as according to an Article of the ſaid Peace, which maketh mention of
Matters in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, notwithſtanding that in ſome Suits they ſhould
declare whether they be Roman Catholiques or not, excuſing themſelves to
give faith to others which they take as parties or as witneſſes;</p>
                  <p>I do alſo command, That concerning this matter there be not
done, nor there ſhall not be done, any thing with thoſe which are born in
the ſaid Realm,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95447:21"/>but only that the ſaid Condition be kept
and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, and that no ſuch queſtions be put unto them gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
unto the Oaths which they ſhall take in Judgement Court, and without, the
ſame faith and credit which ſhould be given in caſe they were
<hi>Spaniards;</hi> and herein you ſhall not receive any trouble or
moleſtation; nor there ſhall not be any grievance done unto you: And
whereas for the juſtification of ſome cauſes, the Judges and Juſtices
do pretend that the Merchants of the ſaid Nation ſhould exhibite Books of
their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions or dealings; I do will and command, that the Books of the
Merchants of the ſaid Nation ſhall not be taken out of their hands for any
cauſe whatſoever, but they ſhall keep and ſhew them in their houſes,
to take out the parcel which ſhall be appointed, and others ſhall not be
demanded of them, nor there ſhall not be any other Papers taken from them,
upon pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty that he which ſhall do here againſt, ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
according to Law.</p>
                  <p>And foraſmuch as the Merchants do diſpatch the Merchandiſe
from the Cuſtom-houſe of the ſaid City of <hi>Sivil</hi> of all Duties,
and becauſe there are many which do make up a ſheet, which is Subſcribed
and Signed by all the Officers, and remaineth in the hand of the
<hi>Alcayde</hi> of the Cuſtom-houſe; for that by vertue thereof, the
Merchandiſes are permitted to go forth, which are in Fardels, Packs, Trunks
and Caſes; and afterwards when they have taken them forth, and put them into
their Houſes and Warehouſes, the chief Keeper of the Cuſtom-houſe, and
the Officers of the half <hi>per Cent.</hi> do viſit the Houſe and Goods,
troubling and moleſting them, demanding of them
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95447:21"/>the diſpatches, it ſeeming unto them,
that they may derain them, becauſe they left the diſpatch in the hands of
the ſaid <hi>Alcayde</hi> of the Cuſtom-houſe; I do prohibit and command,
that the houſes of the ſaid Merchants ſhall not be viſited, nor the
diſpatches ſhall not nor may not be demanded of them, in regard they have
them not in their hands; and this is to be underſtood, and is underſtood of
houſes which are within the Walls of the ſaid City; and to the end it may
be known to you, which are of the Engliſh Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there is to be delivered
unto you Copies of the ſaid Priviledges and Exemptions which do concern you,
and which were granted unto you, as well by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Peace, as by any
other manner. And for exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and accompliſhment of all the Premiſſes,
I do command thoſe of my Council, and thoſe of my Councils, Aſſemblies
and Tribunals of my Court, and the Preſidents and Judges of my Audiences,
<hi>Alcaydes,</hi> and Officers of my Houſe and Court, and Chanceries, and
the Regent and Judge of the Court of Degrees of the City of <hi>Sivil,</hi> and
chief <hi>Alcaldes</hi> of the Precincts thereof, and all the
<hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigidors,</hi> Aſſiſtants, and Governours, chief Juſtices, and
Ordinaries, as well in the ſaid Cities of <hi>Sivil, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diz, Malaga,</hi> and
St. <hi>Lucar de Barameda,</hi> as of all other Cities, Towns and Places, of
theſe my Realms and Dominions, and all other Judges and Juſtices
whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, of what quality or condition ſoever they may be, whom
principally or incidentally may concern in any manner the accompliſhment or
performance of that which is contained in this Patent, that preſently ſo
ſoon as they ſhall be by vertue thereof required, or the Copy thereof
Signed by a Notary publick, that there
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95447:22"/>be thereunto given as much faith, as unto the
Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; and that every one in the place where it ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern him do
obſerve, and accompliſh, and cauſe the ſame to be obſerved,
accompliſhed, and executed, in and for all things as therein is contained,
and they ſhall not in all nor in part put upon you any impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor any
other difficulties or doubts, nor do any thing againſt the tenor and form
thereof, nor conſent or give way that it be interpreted, limited or
ſuſpended in all or in part, or that to the contrary be given any
<hi>Sedidas,</hi> proviſions, or other diſpatches; but for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
thereof, in the place which ſhall concern eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, they ſhall give
order, and ordain to deliver unto you thoſe which ſhall be neceſſary:
And for more firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and validity of the favour and grace which by this my
Patent I do grant you, and that at all times this favour may be certain and
ſure unto you, you are to keep or have a Judge Conſervator in
<hi>Andaluſia,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the ſaid Cities of <hi>Sivil, Malaga,
Cadiz,</hi> and St. <hi>Lucar de Barameda,</hi> unto whom I am to give
ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Commiſſion for keeping and accompliſhing the ſaid
Priviledges, Liberties and Exemptions, who ſhall conſtrain and compell all
and whatſoever perſons, of what ſort or quality they may be that ſhall
concern the ſaid Nation, as well thoſe which ſhall be Defendants
accuſed, as thoſe which ſhall be Plaintiffs, although the perſons which
ſhall accuſe them, and which ſhall be accuſed by them, have private
Judges, as well by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent as agreement which they may have made by
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence or priviledge which they hold, to the end the ſaid Judge
Conſervator may onely take know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge privately of the ſaid Courts, and not
any other
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:95447:22"/>Judge or Tribunall, although it be by way of
exceſs or notorious Juſtice, or in any other matter or form, which Judge
Conſervator is now Doctor <hi>Don Franciſco de Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gara,</hi> Judge of my
Court <hi>de les Grados,</hi> of the City of <hi>Sevill,</hi> the time that he
ſhall aſſiſt therein, and in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence the Licentiate <hi>Don
Franciſco de Modrano,</hi> Judge of the ſame Court, who for the ſuits
which ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced in the ſaid Cities of <hi>Cadiz, Malaga,</hi>
&amp; St. <hi>Lucar,</hi> is to Subdelegate his Conſervatorſhip, in the
perſon which by the ſaid Nation ſhall be propounded or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that he
may effect the ſame to the concluſion, and they ſhall be referred unto
him to be determined: and of that which he ſhall determine, the Appeale is to
be made to my Council, and not to any other Court.</p>
                  <p>And foraſmuch as my will is, that every one in his time
ſhall have primative Commiſſion, and Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to protect and
defend you concerning all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of this my Patent, that all the ſame
may be kept and accompliſhed in the form which I do offer the ſame unto
you, I have found good to charge, as by theſe preſents I do charge them
with the protection and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence hereof: &amp; I do command them to ſee or
peruſe this my Patent, and the qualities, conditions, preheminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and
amplifications therein contained, and to cauſe all the ſame to be kept,
accompliſhed and executed, in ſuch form and manner, and according as
therein is contained and declared, without conſenting or giving way, that in
all, or in part there be made unto you any doubt or difficulty, and before the
ſaid <hi>Don Franciſco de Vergara,</hi> or in his abſence before the
ſaid <hi>Francis de Medrano</hi> (and not before any other Judge) privately
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95447:23"/>in the firſt inſtance, are to paſs, and
be followed all the cauſes and ſuits, which concerning the premiſes, or
any thing or part thereof ſhall be moved and cauſed, and the execution and
puniſhment of thoſe which ſhall not be obedient; For my will is, that the
knowledge and determination of all the contents in this my Patent, is in all
things privately to concern, and ſhall concern them; proceeding in all things
againſt thoſe which ſhall be culpable, and executing for the ſame the
pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties which are mentioned by law, reſerving as I do reſerve, the
appellations which ſhall be put in upon their acts and ſentences, to my
Council, and not any other Court, without that any of other my Councils,
Tribunals, Courts, Chanceries, or any other Judges or Juſtices of my Realms
or Dominions, of whatſoever qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity they be, may meddle, or ſhall meddle
therewith, or in the uſe or exerciſe of the Juriſdiction privative in the
ſaid firſt inſtance, which by this my Patent I do grant unto them, by way
of exceſs, appellation, or any other recourſe or manner; the which and
every of them, I do inhibit and hold for inhibited the knowledge thereof, and
do declare them for incompetent Judges thereof: for which and every thing, and
part thereof, I do give them the moſt ſufficient power, and moſt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
Commiſſion, which according to Law is required and neceſſary, with the
incidences and dependencies, annexities; and after them the ſaid
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation of the ſaid City of <hi>Sivil,</hi> may name in the
ſaid Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion one of the Judges of the ſaid Audience, which the
ſaid Nation ſhall chuſe: And I do command the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and thoſe
of my Council of the Chamber, that preſenting before them their nomination
(the caſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:95447:23"/>happening) to make void the ſaid
Commiſſion, by promotion or vacation of the ſaid <hi>Don Franciſco de
Vergara,</hi> and <hi>Don Francis de Medrano</hi> or to diſpatch it, in any
other manner, by Ordinary to him that ſhall be therein nominated, in the form
according, and as by this my Patent is declared. And that it may be the better
accompliſhed, I do from this time give them power and authority, that they
may Subdelegate, and they ſhall Subdelegate this Commiſſion, for the
buſineſs and Suits which ſhall be offered in the ſaid Cities of
<hi>Cadiz, Malaga,</hi> and St. <hi>Lucar de Berameda,</hi> in the perſon
which by you ſhall be propounded unto them, that they may ſubſtantiate
them for a concluſion, and remit the Suits and Cauſes unto them to be
determined, in ſuch manner as they ſhall find good and convenient, for the
ſecurity of that which is contained in this my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. And I do charge the
moſt excellent Prince, <hi>Don Balthaxar Charles,</hi> my moſt dear and
moſt beloved Son, and do command the Infants, Prelates, Dukes,
Marqueſſes, Earls, Richmen, Commanders, and under-Commanders, Governours of
Caſtles, ſtrong Houſes, and Plains, and thoſe of my Council,
Preſidents, and Judges of my Courts, Alcaydes, and Officers of my Houſe,
Court and Chanceries, and all the Corigidors, Aſſiſtants, Governors,
Alcaldes, Mayors, and Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and whatſoever Judges and Juſtices of
theſe my Realms and Dominions, to obſerve and accompliſh, and cauſe to
be obſerved and accompliſhed, this my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and the favour or Grace
which thereby I do grant you, and againſt the tenor and form thereof, not to
do or paſs, now, nor at any time, in any manner perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for evermore.
Nor to conſent or give way to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:95447:24"/>or ſuſpended unto you, all or part
thereof, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding whatſoever Laws or Statutes of theſe my Realms
and Dominions, Ordinances, Stile, Uſe, or Cuſtom of the ſaid Cities of
<hi>Sivill, Cadiz, Malaga,</hi> or St. <hi>Lucar,</hi> or any other thing which
is or may be to the contrary, the which for this time, forſomuch as
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth this matter, holding the ſame here for inſerted and
incorporated, as it were word for word writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, I do diſpence, abrogate,
derogate, cancel, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilate, and make void and of none effect, remaining in
full force and effect for all other things henceforward. And for this my Patent
<hi>Jeronimo de Canencia,</hi> Auditor of Accompts, in my Chief Office of
Accompts, and my Secretary of the Mediaenate ſhall take a Copy, at whoſe
Charge is the accompt and reaſon of this right. And I do declare, that for
this favour you have paid the duty of the Mediaenate, which amounteth to thirty
and five thouſand one hundred fifty and five Maravediz in Silver: which
ſumme you are to pay from fifteen to fifteen years perpetually, and in caſe
they do accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh or end, you may not make uſe of this favour, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
ſuch time as it ſhall firſt appear that you have ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied this Duty.
And you are alſo to pay the Judge Conſervator, which ſhall be named, his
Salary, or to help to bear his charges, which he ſhall enjoy for his labour
or pains in the ſaid buſineſs, before you ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy thereof, which
is to appear by Certificate of the Office of this Duty.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>Given in
<hi>Saragoſa,</hi> 
                              <date>the nineteenth day of <hi>March, Anno</hi> 1645.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:95447:24"/>
                        <p>I <hi>The King, I</hi> Anthony Carnero, <hi>Secretary of the
King our Lord, did cauſe it to be written, by his Commandment.
Regiſtred,</hi> Michael de Lariaga, <hi>Lieutenant of the Lord High
Chancellor.</hi> Michael de La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riaga. <hi>The Copy was taken,</hi> Jeronimo de
Canencia; Don John Chumazero y Carillo, <hi>Doctor.</hi> Don An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony de Campo
Redondo y Rio, <hi>Licenciate.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>JOSEPH GONSALES.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                           <p>THis Copy doth agree with that out of which it was taken,
which for this effect was exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto me by <hi>William Bland,</hi>
dwelling in the City of <hi>Sivill,</hi> who took it away again with him the
11. of <hi>April, Anno</hi> 1645.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Joſeph de Pineda,</hi> Notary Publick of
the City of <hi>Sivill</hi> for the
King.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </postscript>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
